Climate change is undoubtedly the 21st century
biggest challenge and we must solve it together.
Of course, climate inaction is now the most
economically convenient thing to do but we,
as a species, will have to foot
the bill in the near future.
Our study reveals some key insights into how the
Green Transition could be made financially viable.
Carlo, what's up? What are you doing out so early?
Jacopo, I'm having my morning run!
I saw the sun was out and took the opportunity.
We have had some crazy weather lately.
Yeah, that's climate change kicking in!
You know, I've actually been reading
a few papers about the European
Union Emissions Trading Scheme.
Oh, really? What is it?
It's a way for polluters to exchange their Carbon
Allowances, usually in the form of futures.
But I know it is not a very liquid
and efficient market, isn't it?
Yeah, it was created back in 2005 and it was
very volatile but we are on Phase IV now and
there have been a lot of reforms,
although it 's still very costly
for polluters to trade.
That's called the C-spread.
Oh, come on, let's meet and work on it!
Yeah!
The C-spread, is defined as the following formula.
And we use as F(t,t) the Front December futures,
the futures with expiry in
December of the same year,
which we have found to be the most liquid
and as S(t) we use the Daily Futures.
The C-spread represents the
cost-of-carry, measuring the
difference between the price of Futures
on Carbon Allowances and their spot price.
To compute it, we used a rollover rule
in order to avoid irregularities and
have a unique time-series using
as switch date 15th November.
We also considered Europe's top 10 polluters
and computed the Z-spreads of their bonds,
that is the parallel shift to apply to the
zero-rates in order to match their prices.
We aggregated them and computed a single
time-series, which we called the Z-index.
We plotted the C-spread, Z-index and
Risk-Free Rate in a single image.
As we can see the Z-index and the
C-spread display a long run relationship.
We perform an ADF-GLS test and confirm that the
three time series are integrated of order 1.
We also discover their cointegration
relationship by using the Johansen procedure.
Since the three time-series are not stationary,
we took the time-series of their first-differences
and implemented this error correction model.
As control variables we took three
market indexes and the volatility
of the spot log-returns, which
is estimated with a GARCH model.
As a result, we obtain that the
C-spread is a mean-reverting
process and the Z-index is its main
driver and this is very relevant.
We implemented both Quantile and Linear Regression
because not all hypotheses of the
Linear Regression were satisfied.
And now for the missing
piece of the C-spread puzzle.
For the companies involved there is an
alternative method of financing: a Synthetic Repo.
That is a contract replicating the cashflows of
a traditional repo but using a Carbon Future.
By analyzing the strategy we found that the payer
would be financing itself at the
Risk-Free Rate plus the C-spread.
Finally, including Carbon Allowances into the
list of eligible collateral for Eurosystem
credit operations could help address the
inefficieny of having a positive C-spread.
In finance we are used to thinking
in terms of Profits and Losses,
but mankind's true profit
would be a greener planet.